Guide to the Henry W. Sage papers, 1814-1930.
Sage, Henry W. papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Henry W. Sage papers, 1814-1930.
1155
Henry W. (Henry Williams), Sage, 1814-1897.
60.8 cubic ft; 23 v.; 58 reels mf.; 1 o/s folder.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The Sage papers consists of material pertaining to his business interests, the affairs of Cornell University, and his personal interests.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Lumber magnate, benefactor of Cornell University, president of the Cornell University Board of Trustees.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Sage papers consists of material pertaining to his business interests, the affairs of Cornell University, and his personal interests. The major portion of the papers consists of letterpress copybooks, correspondence, ledgers, daybooks, journals, receipts, land and plat books, and other material pertaining to Sage's many business enterprises, chief among them lumbering, with his partners John McGraw and W. G. Grant; also, to timber land investments and lumber manufacturies at Bell Ewart, Ontario, Canada, and Wenona (later West Bay City) Michigan; to Sage, McGraw and Company, H. W. Sage and Company, Sage Land and Improvement Company, the Michigan Salt Association, Au Gres Company, Rifle River Company, Tittabawassee Company, and Loggers Boom Company. Other papers refer to the acquisition and administration of timber lands in Michigan, Wisconsin, Alabama, Mississippi, Oregon, and California. From circa 1880, Sage invested in railroad and industrial securities; relevant papers pertain to the Wood Heustis Company, Dominick and Dickerman Company, Griswold and Gillette Company, the Atlantic Trust Company, and several other companies, including the Bank of Warsaw in New York, with regard to investments in county bonds.
Other correspondence pertains to Sage's interest in rapid transit lines in Brooklyn, New York, and to the Tehuantepec Canal project in Mexico, the Tehuantepec Inter-Ocean Railroad Company, and the Beech Creek Railroad Company; also, material on mortgage loans in Kansas, Nebraska, and Iowa.
Papers pertaining to Cornell University include correspondence referring to many aspects of the administration of the University and the Board of Trustees as it dealt with such questions as the increased role of the alumni, the selection and retirement of University presidents, the expansion of the physical plant, faculty matters, salaries, the McGraw-Fiske controversy, student conduct, the Cornell Crew and the Henley Regatta, the Wisconsin pinelands of Cornell University, the University Library, the inauguration of Jacob Gould Schurman, and the endowment of the Susan E. Linn Sage Chair of Christian Ethics and Philosophy. Sage's personal interests are documented, including his assistance in the founding of the Cascadilla School, his efforts to persuade Andrew Dickson White to accept the Republican nomination to Congress, correspondence pertaining to phrenology, Sage family genealogy, letters describing the murder in 1837 of Sage's father Charles by Seminole Indians in Florida, and correspondence with his sons Dean and William Henry, and grandson Harry. Major correspondents in the business papers include Augustus Frank, and A. S. Barnes. Pertaining to Cornell, major correspondents include Andrew D. White, Amasa J. Parker, Erastus Brooks, Alonzo B. Cornell, Jacob Gould Schurman, Charles Kendall Adams, Charles Babcock, Mynderse Van Cleef, Francis M. Finch, David Starr Jordan, Russell Sage, Moses Coit Tyler, John DeWitt Warner, and many others.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Sage, Henry W. (Henry Williams), (Henry Williams), 1814-1897.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Brooks, Erastus, 1815-1886.; Cornell, Alonzo B., 1832-1904.; Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Babcock, Chas. (Charles), 1829-1913.; Finch, Francis Miles, 1827-1907.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; Van Cleef, Mynderse, 1853-1935.; Sage, Russell, 1835-1900.; Warner, John DeWitt, 1851-1925.; McGraw, John, 1815-1877.; Grant, W. G.; Sage, Charles.; Sage, William Henry.; Sage, Dean.; Sage, Harry.; Frank, Augustus.; Barnes, A. S.; Parker, Amasa J.; Sage family.; Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902; Babcock, Chas. (Charles), 1829-1913; Barnes, A. S.; Brooks, Erastus, 1815-1886; Cornell, Alonzo B., 1832-1904; Finch, Francis Miles, 1827-1907; Frank, Augustus; Grant, W. G.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; McGraw, John, 1815-1877; Parker, Amasa J.; Sage, Charles; Sage, Dean; Sage family; Sage, Harry; Sage, Russell, 1835-1900; Sage, William Henry; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942; Van Cleef, Mynderse; Warner, John DeWitt, 1851-1925; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918; Sage, McGraw and Company.; H. W. Sage and Company.; Sage Land and Improvement Company.; Michigan Salt Association.; Au Gres Company.; Rifle River Company.; Tittabawassee Company.; Loggers Boom Company.; Wood Heustis Company (New York, N.Y.); Dominick and Dickerman Company (New York, N.Y.); Griswold and Gillete Company (New York, N.Y.); Atlantic Trust Company (New York, N.Y.); Bank of Warsaw (New York, N.Y.); Farson Leach and Company (Chicago, Ill.); Tehuantepec Inter-Ocean Railroad Company.; Beech Creek Railroad Company.; Cascadilla School (Ithaca, N.Y.); Cornell University.; Cornell University. Board of Trustees.; Cornell University -- Students.; Cornell University -- Administration.; Cornell University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Cornell University -- Faculty.; Cornell Crew (Rowing team).; Republican Party (U.S.); Beech Creek Railroad Company; Cascadilla School (Ithaca, N.Y.); Cornell Crew (Rowing team); Cornell University; Cornell University. Board of Trustees; H.W. Sage and Company; Henley Royal Regatta
Subjects:
Business enterprises -- Wisconsin.; Business enterprises -- Michigan.; Business enterprises -- Bell Ewart.; Lumber trade -- Wisconsin.; Lumber trade -- Michigan.; Lumber trade -- Bell Ewart.; Land companies -- Wisconsin.; Land companies -- Michigan; Timber -- Wisconsin.; Timber -- Michigan.; Timber -- Alabama.; Timber -- Mississippi.; Timber -- Oregon.; Timber -- California.; Real property -- Wisconsin.; Real property -- Michigan.; Logging -- Wisconsin.; Business records -- Wisconsin.; Business records -- Michigan.; Securities.; Railroads.; Canals -- Mexico.; Bonds.; Phrenology.; Families -- New York (State); Local transit -- New York (N.Y.); Tehuantepec Canal.; Henley Regatta.; Mortgage loans -- Kansas.; Mortgage loans -- Nebraska.; Mortgage loans -- Iowa.; Seminole Indians.; Transportation -- New York.; Businessmen.; Industrialists.; Bonds; Business enterprises; Business records; Businessmen; Canals; Families; Industrialists; Land companies; Local transit; Logging; Lumber trade; Management; Mortgage loans; Phrenology; Railroads; Real property; Securities; Seminole Indians; Students; Timber; Transportation; Universities and colleges -- Alumni and alumnae; Universities and colleges -- Faculty
Places:
Industries -- Bell Ewart.; Industries -- Wenona.; Industries -- West Bay City.; Industries -- Wisconsin.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Transportation.; Alabama; California; Iowa; Kansas; Mexico; Michigan; Mississippi; Nebraska; New York (State); New York (State) -- New York; New York (State) -- Brooklyn; Oregon; Wisconsin
Form and Genre Terms:
Letterpress copybooks.; Ledgers (account books); Daybooks.; Plat books.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Consists of collections #1155, #1388, and #1557.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Letter Books
Series III. General Papers
Series IV. Microfilm
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1880-03-1882-12 (Box 1)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1883-01-1883-07 (Box 2)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1883-08-1884-02 (Box 3)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1884-03-1884-12 (Box 4)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1885-01-1885-08 (Box 5)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1885-09-1886-02 (Box 6)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1886-03-1886-10 (Box 7)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1886-11-1887-04 (Box 8)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1887-05-1887-10 (Box 9)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1887-11-1888-03 (Box 10)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1888-04-1888-08 (Box 11)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1888-09-1888-12 (Box 12)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1889-01-1889-05 (Box 13)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1889-06-1889-10 (Box 14)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1889-11-1890-02 (Box 15)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1890-03-1890-08 (Box 16)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1890-09-1890-12 (Box 17)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1891-01-1891-05 (Box 18)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1891-06-1891-10 (Box 19)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1891-11-1892-02 (Box 20)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1892-03-1892-08 (Box 21)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1892-09-1892-12 (Box 22)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1893-01-1893-04 (Box 23)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1893-05-1893-09 (Box 24)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1893-10-1894-02 (Box 25)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1894-03-1894-08 (Box 26)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1894-09-1895-01 (Box 27)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1895-02-1895-06 (Box 28)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1895-07-1895-11 (Box 29)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1895-12-1896-03 (Box 30)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1896-04-1896-10 (Box 31)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1896-11-1897-01 (Box 32)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1897-02-1897-07 (Box 33)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1897-08-1897-11-14 (Box 34)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1897-11-15-1898-01 (Box 35)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1898-02-1898-08 (Box 36)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1898-09-1899-05 (Box 37)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1899-06-1900-01 (Box 38)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1900-02-1900-12 (Box 39)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1901-01-1901-12 (Box 40)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1902-01-1902-08 (Box 41)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1902-09-1902-12 (Box 42)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1903-01-1903-12 (Box 43)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1904-01-1904-12 (Box 44)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1905-01-1905-12 (Box 45)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1906-01-1906-12 (Box 46)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1907-01-1907-12 (Box 47)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1908-01-1908-12 (Box 48)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1909-01-1909-12 (Box 49)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1910-01-1910-12 (Box 50)
  - Incoming Correspondence, 1911-01-1911-12 (Box 51)
  - Incoming Correspondence, Undated (Box 52)
- Series II. Letter Books
  - Letter Books, 1857-05-1857-10 (Box 53)
  - Letter Books, 02-1867-11-1867, 02-1871-08-1871 (Box 54)
  - Letter Books, 08-1871-01-1872, 01-1872-06-1872 (Box 55)
  - Letter Books, 06-1872-11-1872, 06-1872-04-1877 (Box 56)
  - Letter Books, 11-1872-April 1873, 04-1873-Set. 1873 (Box 57)
  - Letter Books, 09-1873-03-1874, 03-1874-08-1874, 08-1874-12-1874 (Box 58)
  - Letter Books, 12-1874-05-1875, 05-1875-09-1875 (Box 59)
  - Letter Books, 09-1875-02-1876, 02-1876-05-1876 (Box 60)
  - Letter Books, 07-1876-12-1876, 12-1876-04-1877 (Box 61)
  - Letter Books, 04-1877-08-1877, 08-1877-12-1877, 12-1877-05-1878 (Box 62)
  - Letter Books, 08-1878-10-1878, 10-1878-02-1879, 02-1879-07-1879 (Box 63)
  - Letter Books, 07-1879-12-1879, 12-1879-03-1880 (Box 64)
  - Letter Books, 03-1880-07-1880, 07-1880-11-1880 (Box 65)
  - Letter Books, 11-1880-03-1881, 03-1881-06-1881 (Box 66)
  - Letter Books, 06-1881-11-1881, 11-1881-02-1882 (Box 67)
  - Letter Books, 02-1882-06-1882, 06-1882-11-1882 (Box 68)
  - Letter Books, 11-1882-03-1883, 03-1883-11-1883 (Box 69)
  - Letter Books, 11-1883-04-1884, 04-1884-09-1884, 09-1884-Mar.1885 (Box 70)
  - Letter Books, 03-1885-08-1885, 08-1885-12-1885 (Box 71)
  - Letter Books, 12-1885-05-1886, 05-1886-09-1886 (Box 72)
    Microfilmed
  - Letter Books, 09-1886-01-1887, 01-1887-05-1887 (Box 73)
  - Letter Books, 05-1887-07-1887, 08-1887-11-1887, 11-1887-01-1888 (Box 74)
  - Letter Books, 02-1888-05-1888, 05-1888-09-1888, 09-1888-12-1888 (Box 75)
  - Letter Books, 12-1888-02-1889, 02-1889-06-1889, 06-1889-10-1889 (Box 76)
  - Letter Books, 10-1889-01-1890, 01-1890-04-1890, 04-1890-09-1890 (Box 77)
  - Letter Books, 09-1890-12-1890, 12-1890-03-1891, 03-1891-07-1891 (Box 78)
  - Letter Books, 07-1891-10-1891, 10-1891-01-1892, 01-1892-05-1892 (Box 79)
  - Letter Books, 1891-07-1894-01 (Box 80)
  - Letter Books, 05-1892-09-1892, 09-1892-12-1892, 09-1892-01-3, 1898 (Box 81)
  - Letter Books, 12-1892-03-1893, 03-1893-07-1893, 07-1893-11-1893 (Box 82)
  - Letter Books, 05-1893-11-1894, 11-1894-10-1896 (Box 83)
  - Letter Books, 11-1893-02-1894, 02-1894-08-1894 (Box 84)
  - Letter Books, 08-1894-01-1895, 01-1895-07-1895 (Box 85)
  - Letter Books, 07-1895-12-1895, 12-1895-07-1896 (Box 86)
  - Letter Books, 07-1896-04-1897, 04-1897-12-1897 (Box 87)
  - Letter Books, 10-1896-08-1898, 08-1898-02-1900 (Box 88)
  - Letter Books, 1897-10-1899-11 (Box 89)
  - Letter Books, 07-1898-06-1899, 06-1899-04-1900 (Box 90)
  - Letter Books, 1899-11-1902-04 (Box 91)
  - Letter Books, 02-1900-02-1902, 02-1902-05-1903 (Box 92)
  - Letter Books, 04-1900-05-1901, 05-1901-07-1902 (Box 93)
  - Letter Books, 1902-04-1904-01 (Box 94)
  - Letter Books, 1903-05-1904-07 (Box 95)
  - Letter Books, 07-1902-12-1904, 12-1904-07-1908 (Box 96)
  - Letter Books, 07-1904-10-1905, 10-1905-01-1907 (Box 97)
  - Letter Books, 01-1907-10-1908, 07-1908-12-1923 (Box 98)
- Series III. General Papers
  - Deeds, etc., 1829-1859 (Box 99)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1860-1869 (Box 100)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1870-1879 (Box 101)
  - Receipts for Land Sales, 1871-1874 (Box 102)
  - Tax Receipts, 1873-1875 (Box 103)
  - Taxes, 1874-1875, 1879-1880 (Box 104)
  - Tax Receipts, 1875-1878 (Box 105)
  - Accounts, 1876-1877 (Box 106)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1878-1879 (Box 107)
  - Tax Receipts, 1880-1884 (Box 108)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1881-1884 (Box 109)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1882-1883 (Box 110)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1882-1901 (Box 111)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1884-1885 (Box 112)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Papers, 1887-1889 (Box 113)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1889-1912 (Box 114)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1890-1897 (Box 115)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1890-1899 (Box 116)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1890-1899 (Box 117)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1891-1901 (Box 118)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1893-1897 (Box 119)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1894-1897 (Box 120)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1896-1898 (Box 121)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1898-1899 (Box 122)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1900-1901 (Box 123)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1900-1908 (Box 124)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1902-1903 (Box 125)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1902-1903 (Box 126)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1902-1903 (Box 127)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1904-1906 (Box 128)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1906-1907 (Box 129)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1907-1909 (Box 130)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1909-1927 (Box 131)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1910-1914 (Box 132)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1910-1914 (Box 133)
  - Bills, Rent Receipts, 1928-1938 (Box 134)
  - Miscellaneous Letters + Finances, Undated (Box 135)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Undated (Box 136)
    20 volumes
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Undated (Box 137)
    4 volumes
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Undated (Box 138)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Undated (Box 139)
  - Incoming Mail, 1882-1890 (Box 140)
    Microfilmed for Wisconsin
  - Incoming Mail, 1891-1907 (Box 142)
    23 volumes; microfilmed for Wisconsin
- Series IV. Microfilm
  - Microfilm Reel, 1885-12-07-1886-05-08; Reel 1
  - Microfilm Reel, 1886-05-08-1886-09-06; Reel 2
  - Microfilm Reel, 1886-09-06-1887-01-13; Reel 3
  - Microfilm Reel, 1887-01-14-1887-05-12; Reel 4
  - Microfilm Reel, 1887-05-12-1887-07-28; Reel 5
  - Microfilm Reel, 1887-08-24-1887-11-21; Reel 6
  - Microfilm Reel, 1887-11-21-1888-01-30; Reel 7
  - Microfilm Reel, 1888-02-11-1888-05-31; Reel 8
  - Microfilm Reel, 1888-05-31-1888-09-04; Reel 9
  - Microfilm Reel, 1888-09-04-1888-12-13; Reel 10
  - Microfilm Reel, 1888-12-13-1889-02-28; Reel 11
  - Microfilm Reel, 1889-02-27-1889-06-29; Reel 12
  - Microfilm Reel, 1889-06-29-1889-10-14; Reel 13
  - Microfilm Reel, 1889-10-14-1890-01-16; Reel 14
  - Microfilm Reel, 1890-01-17-1890-04-30; Reel 15
  - Microfilm Reel, 1890-04-30-1890-09-02; Reel 16
  - Microfilm Reel, 1890-09-02-1890-12-18; Reel 17
  - Microfilm Reel, 1890-12-18-1891-03-04; Reel 18
  - Microfilm Reel, 1891-03-04-1891-07-03; Reel 19
  - Microfilm Reel, 1891-07-03-1891-10-22; Reel 20
  - Microfilm Reel, 1891-10-22-1892-01-22; Reel 21
  - Microfilm Reel, 1892-01-22-1892-05-12; Reel 22
  - Microfilm Reel, 1892-05-12-1892-09-21; Reel 23
  - Microfilm Reel, 1892-09-21-1892-12-28; Reel 24
  - Microfilm Reel, 1892-12-24-1893-03-25; Reel 25
  - Microfilm Reel, 1893-03-27-1893-07-23; Reel 26
  - Microfilm Reel, 1893-07-24-1893-11-15; Reel 27
  - Microfilm Reel, 1892-09-24-1897; Reel 28